hello and welcome to the 20th tutorial
on how to program in g-script 2.
so
i deleted all this code we did in the
last tutorial and i replaced it with two
arrays
xx and yy both with 100 variables in
them
now when we're calling arrays
we can put we can just put the name of
the array
or xx and put a number like n
which would be the 11th variable
remember because the variable start at
zero and go to whatever this is minus
one
so
equals
like
five
but there's another way to do it let's
make a
let's make a variable temp dot
sum bar is equal to one
or ten
we can replace
ten in the variable brackets with
temp dot sum
bar or just sum sumbar because
temp variables don't require the
beginning to be specified after they've
been created
so anyway
let's create a for loop
now this loop is going to create a
variable called n
loop until it reaches 100 or something
greater than 99
which is 100 and then it's gonna break
now because we're working with
arrays we can't go to 100
because remember
the variables start at one
i mean the variable started
the value of like zero
i don't know if this is i'm confusing
you
but the highest
variable to like specify would be 99
because it starts at zero it doesn't
start at one starts at zero it creates
100 variables but when you're calling
them
you have to do whatever you want minus
one
well that's kind of confusing but i
think you'll get it
anyway
let's add
xx
and
we're taking this
variable and putting it inside the
brackets of the array to specify which
variable in the array we want to change
let's make them all equal to
int
random
0 comma
64.
so we're going to make xx
each each of the xx variables because
we're looping through all of them we're
going to make each of them equal to a
value between 0 and 64.
same with y
remember that every level has 64 tiles
to the right and 64 tiles
down
if we're
taking it as the origin being the top
left corner which it is
now let's create
let's call a function on timeout
i'm gonna make it so that it
loops through this
function
and let's add another for loop
so every you know let's add some things
first
x x
n equals x x n
minus
you know plus 0.2
and then yy
n
equals yy
minus
no plus one
so we're going to go into this for loop
and it's going to go it's going to loop
through all the variables in the array
and change them all
by 0.1
change all the
variables anyway by whatever
is here
so once that's changed it's going to
loop
back to the beginning of the function
and change them again and again and
again and this will happen every 0.05
seconds which is
pretty quick
so let's add some more stuff
right here
let's show an image show image
200 plus n we don't want to we don't
want it to be under 200 because that'll
be shown for everyone and it'll be laggy
that way
then let's go
let's
pick and
pick an image you want to use let's just
use block.png
because i don't think i have a rain
image well i do i just remember the name
but then let's add
x x n as the x coordinate and
y-y and has the y-coordinate
just watch what no wait we want to add
one more thing
i want to add if
xx actually i'm going to add that after
this we're going to run as you can see
all of them just
keep going down
each of these blocks is a different
variable with two variables in the
arrays
each with an x x and a y y coordinate
and each of them is different but
they're all changing
at the same rate
let's add it so that they go back to the
top after they reach the bottom
if
x x
n
is
less than
no we want y y n x x y y n
is
greater than
64 which is the very bottom of the
level then
we want it yy to reset so let's add yy
actually we can just copy this here
we want the variable or both variables
to be set and go back to a random point
actually we don't want y to be anywhere
i wanted to be at the very top
so let's add
zero
and watch what happens
they keep coming down and then going
back up
so that's pretty useful and you can do a
lot of things with arrays such as
particle effects and among other things
well that concludes this tutorial and i
hope you have a better understanding of
arrays and we'll be sure to use them
more later so if you don't understand
them you can either
go to
the graw forums and look for some
examples or go to the girl wiki and
grow gscript wiki and
look at some things i don't know
whatever
that can whatever can help you
but i'm probably gonna i'm gonna be
using them more in the future so
you can wait for a tutorial like that to
come out but anyway that's the end of
this tutorial and i'll see you later